<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="fossato@pow2.com">Luca Fossato</author>
    <title>DbForms</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Overview">
  <p>
    DbForms enables developers to build sophisticated web-based database driven applications in very short time 
	and with very little efforts. DbForms - applications are built in a manner conceptually similar to RAD - 
	database building tools such as Microsoft Access (for Windows-based applications) or Sybase PowerSite 
	(for web-based applications). 
  </p>
  <p>
    Rapid Application Development (RAD) tools in general, allow a user to place database components and 
	action elements on templates which then get executed at runtime.  As you will soon discover, dbForms 
	uses these same techniques for its own framework.
  </p>
  <p>
    An important benefit of using DbForms is its openness to other systems. You may use DbForms in conjunction 
	with common JSP-pages, Struts-based pages, etc. This means that you are free to use DbForms where it brings 
	you the most benefits (dramatically reduce development efforts, etc.) and to use other techniques if you 
	think that they offer a better solution.  
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Architecture">
  <p>
    DbForms implements the concepts of the Model - View - Controller design pattern
	and leads to typical 3-tiered web-applications.
  </p>
  <p>
    <img src="images/mvc.gif" border="0" />
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Technical background">
  <p>
    DbForms is based on the following specifications: 
	"Java Servlets 2.3" and "Java Server Pages 1.2" by Sun 
	Microsystems. 
	For more information on server-side Java technology please 
	see <a href="http://www.javasoft.com/products/servlets/"> [servlet]</a>
  </p>
  <p>
    DbForms makes extensively use of the "JSP Tag Library Extension" included in the JSP 1.1 specification. 
    <a href="http://www.javasoft.com/products/jsp/taglibraries.html">[tags] </a>
  </p>
  <p>
    <!--
      XML parsing facilities and other parts of DbForms are based on code taken from Apache Group's 
      Jakarta-Struts project. <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">[Struts]</a>
    -->
      XML parsing facilities and other parts of DbForms use <a href="http://www.apache.org">Apache</a> Group's XML components:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://xml.apache.org/xerces2-j/" target="_top">Xerces</a> XML parser</li>
        <li><a href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/"   target="_top">Xalan</a> XSLT processor</li>
        <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/digester.html" target="_top">Digester</a> component</li>
      </ul>
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Contacts">
  <p>
    Any questions or comments? Please send an E-Mail to the <a href="mail-lists.html"> mailing list</a>!
  </p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
